So now we're gonna switch from my little point class which is just two doubles to an actual string class.
So what's interesting about the Python string class is that you can extend it and so we've been
talking a lot about pointers and arrays and even when you call malloc you can't just keep extending
things whereas in Python thankfully we can just extend things. We create a string, we can append
an H to it, we can print it, append "lo world" and print it and then assign it to some other string
and then print that and get its length and we never had to allocate or deallocate any memory
during this time. When you get done looking at the code what we're going to have to do to allocate
and deallocate memory what you should be thinking is wow I'm glad I'm programming in Python. I'm glad
that Guido Van Rossum gave me a string class rather than a character array of fixed length,
an expandable string class rather than a character array of fixed length. So we're going to
create in C using our little convention of naming a string class and so if we look at the code what
we're going to try to do here is we're going to basically emulate the Python syntax but in C.
So we're going to start by making a structure, pyster structure, we're going to get a pointer
back, we're going to name that x, we're going to call the constructor pyster new, we're going to
dump it, we're going to have a little dumper, we're going to append an H to it, we're going to dump
it again, then we're going to append a whole string. Now H in C is a character and "lo world"
is a multi-character string and so we're appending many characters. We're going to dump that then
we're going to assign it to a completely new string and then we're going to print it out like
pi give me the string version of this object or the length of it and then we're going to delete it
throw it away. So you can see all of the Python operations are sort of mimicked but with naming
conventions in C. Now the one thing you'll notice here is in this main code we never allocated any
memory and we never de-allocated any memory. That is within the object. Now within the object we
have a responsibility to properly allocate and de-allocate but one of the interesting things
here is is I haven't shown you the code to do any of that and so you don't know that but that's cool
because we can use this as long as we do a new play with it and then do a del we can do stuff
with it it underneath pyster it does all of that memory management for us and that's one of the
beautiful things about an object-oriented approach. Again the syntax on the one side in C is pretty
heavy but in the syntax on the on the other side which is the the Python is pretty light
but the idea is is that in Python we never had to worry about over making a string too long or too
short or having buffer overrun or anything like that. So as we dive in we have to realize that
part of the job of this pyster object is to handle all memory allocation on our behalf so we as
programmers can write much simpler code. Okay so now we are going to build the pyster class. We're
going to create a structure called pyster and in that we're going to have three things the length
of the string we have how much data we've got allocated in the string and then char data is
the actual character array and so we have to have a character array inside of it. We're not we're
not going to let the outside code touch this character array directly we're going to completely
manage it inside this object. We draw a little bubble around us and it's like you can do stuff
you can use my object but I'm going to deal with everything for you so don't mess around with my
internal stuff. So what we would think of is all of this instruct pyster is sort of private and see
we don't have a good way to force it to be private but in the concept of object orientation length
alloc and data would be something we'd think of it as private. In our constructor we are being asked
to create a new python string and we're going to return a pointer to that structure when it's done.
So the first thing we do is we alloc alloc it now int int is usually 32 bits so that's four
alloc there's four eight there's probably 16 characters in pyster. When we do malloc size
of p is 16 that's the number 16 and so it's going to give me 16 characters. Now the the key
thing is is that that is not allocating the actual string data it's just allocated eight
bytes for a pointer to the string. Star data is a pointer and that first malloc is only giving us
the pointer not the actual data. So then we just sort of set it up we say our length of the string
is zero there's nothing in it our allocated length of the underlying data string is 10 and then we
immediately call malloc to get 10 characters so now data is a 10 character character array and
alloc tells us how much we've allocated because it's our job inside this thing to keep track of
that stuff and then just to be good we throw backslash zero at the zero position in that
allocated character we don't know what the rest of them are we just know that the first one is zero
and then we return the pointer to the structure not the pointer to the data the pointer to the
structure and this gets called inside the main as struct pyster star x equals pyster new and when
we're done we get back this cool little two pieces of data that have been dynamically allocated and
it's all it's all ready for us to do cool stuff with we got the struct we've got the constructor
and then we've got the destructor which is pyster del and that again passes in self now we're calling
free now if you recall there are two allocated things one is the data which is the character
array that we've got we've got to get rid of that and then we got to get rid of the object itself
and so at the end of del we have given back all of the data that we've alloc'd now one thing
important here is the order of these two statements matters a lot so when we free self we're not
supposed to access self anymore after that point i'm i'm sure there could be some data just laying
in there that's not been ruined but you just don't know and so that's why we have to free self
arrow data before we free self just because it's just wrong to do that in the other order and so
we do a pyster dump and in that we dump out the length we dump out how much we've allocated so far
and what the data is in it so far and then pyster len pyster len returns an integer and it takes
self as a parameter the key to this is it returns self length and you might ask why it is that we
don't just let our calling code access self length and this again is encapsulation we don't want to
reveal the fact that we're keeping track of length in this variable because we don't want the calling
code to be messing with it remember that length data and alloc are kind of private and so instead
of saying just go look at self length no i would like you to call my function and i will give you
the thing you want so you just call the len function to pass in the instance and that allows
me to change the name of length it allows me to interpret length differently allows me to do all
kinds of things but at least the object writer is in control of the contract with the outside world
so by hiding all the data and giving methods to act we call these accessors to access this data
is a good idea now the underscore stir if you think of python it's like you can say stir open
paren close paren anything inside the parentheses and it converts it to a string well it just so
happens that we're going to maintain self dot data as a valid string so when you say take this
string object and convert it to a string ready for printing i'm just going to return the pointer
to the string we've been maintaining all along internally we have some other methods that we've
got to add we've got a add an append to add a single character you can see that it's got
two parameters it's got self and a single character ch you got append s which is a got two
parameters the self the instance and a whole character string which is a pointer to a character
then we have a sign which is uh got two parameters one is self and one is a pointer to a character
string now i'm not going to give you these lines of code i'm going to give you an assignment to
write these lines of code i'm going to show you how they're supposed to work but i'm not going to
give you the code so i'm telling you that pyster append is about 10 lines of code pyster append s
is just one line of code it's a for loop pyster assign is about three lines of code so pyster
append s calls pyster append and pyster assign calls pyster append s and so we do a lot of reuse
here so let's take a look at how these are going to be used in our main program we say struct pyster
star x equals pyster new which is give me a new string object and then we're going to append a
single character h to it and then we're going to append s a multi-character string and we're going
to dump it each time and then we're going to overwrite our object with a completely new string
and so the key thing is you have got to build this this is what you're going to build okay but
i'm talking a little bit about how to do it so let's walk through what you might need to do in
pyster append now recall that when we set this thing up we created length we allocated 10 characters
and a 10 character array and had data point to that 10 character array and we remembered that we
had 10 characters so the first thing that append does is it checks if the the the length is greater
than what we've allocated meaning that you know if we're going to put in character zero like the
letter h we can just append it and then update length we still have 10 characters allocated and
we've used one of them and so we can just start appending into data right and we have to put in
zero at the after it so that the data is a valid string all the time and so if you kind of imagine
that we create the new object we have a new object it has a length of zero and it has 10 character
array and it has a string end character in the first character we're good we have 10 allocated
and we know we have 10 allocated then if we add an h character single character h all we have to do
is add h into that array data sub zero in that case and then update length to be one and then say
data sub one is backslash zero so that we terminate it correctly so after that first line
the data is h it's a valid h string so we've appended a single character we've updated the
length and then we have terminated the string and then we go to the next line and see where we're
just in this case we're going to append the letter e and we look at the length of the of it because
it tells us where to put it the length is one so we put it in sub one and add backslash zero and
then we check to make sure that we have space for it because we've got 10 but we've only used two
we really use three because h e end of character string so we really use three but the length of
the string we've got is three so as long as no one asks us to append more than 10 characters
append is a pretty simple operation you just add to the the character array that we've already got
allocated okay but of course it gets interesting you can pen h e l l o space w o r and at that
point we have uh nine characters in our length of the string that's in data is nine we've got
it properly terminated so we have used the 10th character to terminate the string so we're really
good things are great but now the problem is we have got to append the l after the r so we have
to append the l after the r so what we have to do is we have to call a function we called malloc
in the constructor and now in append we're going to have to call realloc to say oh i asked for 10
characters but now i want to extend that from 10 to 20 characters and realloc does that realloc
says here's a pointer and it knows how many characters it is please reallocate this pointer
take this date in this pointer and give me make it 20 long instead of 10 long it might have to
copy it so let's take a look at what realloc does so we can extend the size of a dynamically
allocated area by calling realloc with the current pointer to the area and the new size
so in the constructor you see that we malloc 10 and then we're in the append and we say if
the length is greater than self alloc minus two we don't have space for two characters left then
we're going to have to realloc so what we're going to do is we're going to change this from
10 to 20 characters so we're going to take self alloc which is 10 and add 10 to it so now self
alloc is 20 and then we're going to set self data to a to realloc the old self data 20 characters
so this this realloc takes a pointer and a new size and gives us back a new pointer now it
actually may have to move it in memory so you can't assume that self data is the same before and
after but you can assume that if it had to move the data to find you a 20 character slot in its
free space that it will have copied all the first 10 characters will be copied and then
you'll get a new parameter and that's why you see self data on both sides both in the call to realloc
and as the assignment statement so we go back here and we can see that oh yeah now we have 20
and it's got plenty of space for the l and the d and the backslash zero so now we're going to
show the code that's going to basically test our class we're going to create a new we're going to
dump it we're going to append a single character h we're going to dump it we're going to append a
string one way to make this simple is just have append s call append repeatedly for nine characters
because appending nine character string is the same as appending nine characters not appending one
character time nine times then assign assigning a completely new string which means that you got to
you got to take length back and you got to set some things and you got to check the size and
do a whole bunch of stuff and then we're going to ask the pyster underscore stir to give us back a
printable string and then we're going to ask the pister underscore length to tell us how long this
thing is and so you get to write some code not too much code probably 15 lines of code but it is code
that you will need to think deeply about and you're going to need to understand the structures you're
going to need to understand the pointers etc etc etc up next we are going to make a list class
so