So now we're going to build a Python Dictionary class.
And here is the code that we would put in our dictionary.
I kept the strings really short because of all the,
I want the examples to be pretty short and easy.
So what do we do?
We create a dictionary and we use the, you know,
bracket square bracket operator to create a key.
It's a key value pair.
The key Z match it goes to catch phrase, we print it out.
The dictionary Z goes to W,
which is replacing catchphrase with W.
'Cause if you overwrite the same key,
you have to put the same, you have to replace the value.
And then we're going to throw three more things.
Y maps to B, C maps to capital C, and A maps to D.
That's just so that it's not sorted too badly.
And then I print it out.
And then I print the length of it.
I do a get and with a default value of 404.
So sometimes I get that for Z,
I get the W and then for X is not there.
So I get the 404.
Again, kind of an homage to the HTTP error code 404 not found.
And then I use it right over a little for loop
for key and dict, et cetera.
I can print the key value pairs out.
We'll do the same thing in C.
And again, this is almost a perfect transformation, literally.
We first create the dictionary with calling a new,
then we put the word catchphrase in the Z key,
then we print it, then we put a W in the Z key,
which should override it, and we print that.
And then we set the Y key to be B, the C to be capital C,
the A to be capital D, and then we print that.
And then we ask, how long is it?
And then we do a get to look up under the Z key
and the X key, one of which is there,
one of which is not there.
And I get a null back in that situation.
I guess I was a little C like in my get code.
And then I dump it out and I do a struct DNode loop
go from the head until it's null and I print out the key
and the value from each of those dictionary nodes.
And then I delete it at the end.
So this is the code.
Now again, notice we don't know much about looking things up.
We don't know how the length is maintained.
We don't know how the static and dynamic allocation
is going to happen.
We now have a contract with a bunch of library code
that is going to implement this dictionary object for us
and do all of them memory manipulation on our behalf.
Again, we start with the basic stuff.
The big thing we're going to do
is we're going to not just have a value.
It looks a lot like a linked list.
We're going to have a key value pair.
The py dict has a head and a tail and a count,
just like the py list.
And if you look at the constructor,
it's pretty much like the constructor for the list.
We allocate the dict py dict structure
and we set the head and tail to null to indicate empty.
And we set the count to zero and we're done.
And the same with the del.
The del is very much like the linked list del.
Because we've allocated the key, the key
is also going to be a dynamically allocated
pointer to a character array.
So we got a free curr key along with curr value.
But then everything else is the same.
We preload the next value, then we free curr,
then we move to the next value.
And then when it's all said and done,
we free self, which is the py dict value.
When it's all said and done, we can call the new
and then we can set a key, like catchphrase.
And the key thing there is the key and value
are both malloced bits of memory.
Just like before we had the text,
which was a malloced bit of memory and copied
and we had to free it.
But now we just have two things.
And so the key and the value are two things
that are going to be malloced and then copied
into the malloced area.
So some methods for you to build.
The lens should be pretty easy.
Similarly, we have a print that's going to be pretty
and I want you to match exactly the output of the Python.
And so it turns out that we can make a method called find,
which returns a DNode rather than get returns a string
and find returns a DNode.
And then we can use find both in get and in put.
Now we use it pretty much in get to go find it
and then return the value because we have the key.
We look up find it by key and then return the value.
So that's pretty easy to do the get once you have find.
So the find is a for loop where you're going to go
and you're going to find it.
And if you find it, you're going to send it back.
And if you're not, you're going to send a null back.
Now you better check if it's null, right?
Including in the get, you've got to check if it's null.
But then in the put, what you do is
you look up the old one with pydict_find.
And if you get one, if old is not equal to null,
then you're updating the key, updating the value for the key.
And if not, you're adding it.
Now the thing about the else clause here
is it looks a lot like a linked list.
Because really if you look at this thing,
it is a linked list.
It's just there's two values in each one.
We're not doing anything magical.
Now more advanced dictionary implementations
might use hash maps or binary trees or other things
like that, like that we're in chapter six that we
didn't talk too much about.
But for now, we're just going to make our dictionary
be a linked list.
But instead of just a value, it's a key and a value.
So we can look it up by key.
And so we're not doing too much tricky stuff
to make our dictionary really by just adding a bit to a list.
So let's just take a look at how this
is going to work in sort of the real world as it runs.
So remember, we have kind of the dictionary
itself, which is a head and a tail and a count.
And then we have the dictionary nodes,
which is our key and value.
And the next one, now the key and the value
are not the actual strings.
They're just pointers to strings,
which means we're going to have to use malloc.
When we get a key and we get a value,
we're going to have to malloc and copy both of those things.
So if we start and we see pydict_new,
we're going to get a dictionary with head and tail
that point to null.
And then if we add catchphrase, well, we allocate the z.
We allocate and copy the key z.
And we allocate and copy the value and put those in key.
And then next is null and head and tail point to this thing.
So we've allocated three things.
We've allocated a DNode.
And we've allocated two character arrays using malloc.
So then let's say we're going to run the next line of code,
which is setting the key z to w.
Now when you're in the put code, you go and you call find.
And you see that there is a thing.
There is already a z in there.
So what you've got to do is you've
got to replace catchphrase.
So you actually, before you go and make a new value,
you then copy w into it.
You want to free the old stuff.
And so you tend to free the value that was in there before.
And then you malloc and copy in for the new value.
So if you're done, at the end of this,
you will have catchphrase somewhere in magic free space.
We don't know how C does magic free space, but it does do it.
So at the end of the second put, you
still have one entry, but the value
has been changed from pointing at catchphrase
to pointing at w.
Then we add y equals b.
Well, you do a find and there is no y key.
So now it's more like a linked list.
You create a new D node and you append it to the end,
just like in a linked list.
And then you save the key and point key at it.
And then you save the value into new malloc space
and then point value at that.
And then we go to the next one, where we point C,
that we don't find C in there.
So we create a new D node.
And then we do a malloc of the key and a malloc of the value.
And we point to those and then copy the data
into those two malloced areas.
And then point key and value at those malloced areas.
And you can kind of see that this is really, at this point,
unless we find the key in there already,
it's just a linked list that happens
to have two character arrays that are dynamically
allocated and copied, one for key, one for value.
That was a bunch of object orientation.
It was kind of a walk down the path
that Guido van Rossum took probably
in the first few weeks of him building the string
class, list class, and dictionary class.
Chances are good, he built something very, very similar.
And then he's like, OK, now I've got to make this better.
But if I was just writing this thing,
he'd probably just type this out.
It's kind of pretty for computer scientists
who've been doing algorithm data structures their whole lives.
It's like, well, why don't I just make a class that does this?
Now that I've got sort of an object oriented universe,
let me hide all of the dynamic memory.
And that's really what we're doing.
We're hiding the dynamic memory and the implementation details
and all the for loops and while loops are being hidden.
They're important.
And if you were to look at the source code
to str, list, and dict in Python,
you'd see they're allocating and reallocating.
They're doing it a lot more cleverly than what we did.
You don't want to call realloc too many times,
but for now it works.
We're doing small stuff.
There is an infinite number.
There's an infinite array of optimizations
to make all of this way faster and more impressive.
But that's really for another time.
So we've kind of got the idea of the baby steps
from a procedural language with pointers, structures,
and dynamic memory allocation.
How you would take the step using those underlying things
in a procedural language to build basic objects
and support those objects, perhaps as you're building
a new language like Python.