So I want to talk about the C++ programming language for just a bit because C++ plays a really,
really important role in the development of object-oriented programming. C of course came
out like '72 through '78 and then C++ came out in '80 and then both C++ and C co-evolved through
the early 1980s and then you see things like C# and Java and Python and PHP all informed heavily
by C++. If we look at how object-oriented was happening kind of before C++, it was like C++
wasn't really appreciated by the typical mainstream procedural programmer of the day
and so things like ALGOL and Simula, it was kind of like there were tribes that liked procedural
and tribes that liked object-oriented. But then C++ came along and sort of pretty much unified it,
which meant that you probably learned Python as your first programming language and you were using
object-oriented programming from the time that you started and C++ is what sort of unified that
and it was the C++ as the quickly number one procedural programming language and then C++
as the number one object-oriented programming language that kind of brought order to the notion
of procedural, object-oriented, hybrid, etc. and sort of everything that kind of came after 1980
was really strongly influenced and informed by C and C++. So let's take a look at how this
sort of changed over time by looking at some syntactical influence. So C++, which was the
earliest, which is a preprocessor plus a compiler, it turned into a compiler on its own eventually,
but it has this concept of a map that has a separately selectable type of the key, type of
the value, and it uses the square brackets, map open square bracket, z closed square bracket equals
eight, and that is in effect a put. That's like a insert into the map or update of the key and it's
a pretty succinct syntax and so Python came up with a way. Python really didn't want to make a
more complex syntax than C++, so Python worked on its language to make it so that you could just say
d equals d i c t and it was a typeless language and so we don't care the fact that it's going
to be strings mapping to integers because you can map lots of things to lots of things in Python,
but it did follow the d sub z equals eight and again you you use this from the beginning when
you first started programming in Python and you thought that was just natural, but what's really
going on is more like what Java did in 1995. We're not going to use the square bracket to do
put stuff into a map. We're going to be more pure here and we're going to create methods. Now if you
look under the covers in Python you see that that is really a method that does that insert of the
key of z and the value of eight, but if you look at Java it says map string integer so we again
have this notion of a generic class capital map map string integer map which is our object variable
equals new tree map string integer which of course is choosing the underlying implementation
and then they have the syntax of a setter style map dot put and then they're giving the key and
the value as two different parameters. There's choices that each of these languages are making
and I'll try to highlight them as we go through it. I want to talk a little bit about how C++
and its object-oriented approach and design made it so that a class like the map works almost the
same as like a sort of a low level class like a float or an int and it has access in particular
to kind of the special characters or operators like square brackets or plus or minus how that
happens and it is that you can create a specially named method inside of a C++ class that the
compiler will consult and call when it encounters certain what you think of as language syntax
meaning that as it's parsing the language syntax like square brackets it's like oh I've got some
code to do some work here this concept is called operator overloading meaning that the operator
the behavior of the operator is controlled by the writer of the class you are writing a class so in
this bit of code here I've created for no particular reason a a class that I call 10 integers in a row
and I have a array of 10 integer values but that's private so that's something that the
outer class can't talk to right so you can't say 10 and 10 like in the main you 10 dot values is
like no you're not allowed to touch that because it's private but then what I do is I create a
public method which is the square brackets operator method the method to be called when
the compiler encounters square brackets my class name my object name followed by square brackets
call me now the first thing we see is the return type of this operator square bracket operator code
is an integer reference an integer that can either be read or written which means it can be on the
left or right hand side of an assignment statement and the parameter that it's being given is an
integer index which is the thing inside of the square brackets now it is a reference because of
the ampersand but it is a constant reference meaning we are not allowed to change it inside
of this function okay so const means we're leaving it alone which means we are not allowed to say
index equals 42 inside the operator the square bracket operator method and so what we're returning
is that private variable values sub index but we are returning a reference to it so wherever it
appears in the original c++ code in the main what happens is that reference can be like I said on
the left or right side of an assignment state so let's take a look at how this works in the main
code I am going to create a variable called 10 of type 10 int and I say 10 sub 1 equals 40 which
means I'm storing 40 in position 1 but when it sees that 10 sub 1 it says oh oh this little class
has an operator square bracket operator so I better call that little method pass the 1 in then
that returns a reference to values sub 1 and then into that reference the 40 is assigned now python
doesn't have return a reference and it doesn't have a call a reference c kind of does but it's
very they're pointers and so references and pointers are different references you'll notice
there's no special syntax to dereference a reference whereas you when you get a pointer
you got to have special syntax to dereference a pointer so this notion of call by reference
and return by reference is like impressive in c++ and allows it to do a lot of things
and allows us to have this seemingly native line of code 10 sub 1 equals 40 which is really just
a bunch of method calls amazing and then we immediately say print 10 sub 1 contains and then
10 sub 1 and again when this is kind of a right hand side of an assignment statement it's looking
it up it calls the method the operator the square bracket operator method passes 1 into it and then
we return values sub 1 and then that's what gets printed out and so then we say 10 sub 5 equals 10
sub 1 plus 2 and now we see 10 sub 1 on the right hand side of an assignment statement which calls
that same code in the operator brackets method within the class passes in the 1 returning the
reference to value sub 1 but then that reference is just 40 and then we add 2 to it and then we
assign it into 10 sub 5 which is again calling the in operator method to get a reference to values
sub 5 and that assignment happens all i really did was kind of faked it but i i used it to show you
this like lovely ability to do operator overloading when i first found my way into java
my greatest disappointment and because i taught a c++ class and then i learned java i wasn't a
wiz at c++ but i really thought it was pretty elegant so for me my brain was so i didn't learn
python first i learned c++ first and i'm like hey that's what object oriented ought to be
and then i'm like i'm going java and java didn't do that java basically does not want and did not
want as a choice to take values by reference in method calls and even more it did not want to
return references in the return values of method calls that those two things the ampersand in the
return type and the ampersand in the call parameter call those are essential for c++ to accomplish
this and java did not want to return references in particular because it has to do with garbage
collection variables going out of scope etc etc if you return a reference you don't know when it's
out of scope etc um these are powerful complex and potentially quite dangerous things right
but the c++ design was hey you are a samurai warrior and you are going to
you are going to use these very wisely and we don't want to take power away from you we want
to give you all the power that you might want and just trust that you're not going to make mistakes
right and so choices that java make and python make are like no no no we don't want you to make
mistakes so we're not even going to give you this kind of thing but there are other ways to do
everything uh things like tuple returns in c is a good example of um kind of an homage to this
notion of returning things is not always just a single thing so um but c++ is kind of unique now
again um python emulated the c syntax that was quite beautiful that was a result of c's support
for operator overload and here's the here's the thing where like it all comes together so python
saw the beautiful syntax that c++ when you did the right things the compiler would give you this
let you use this beautiful syntax and still call your methods inside the object but they didn't
want to do the call by reference and return by re return reference that c++ did and so what they
did is they did basically a syntax transformation if you look python is in a sense very java like
in that everything has to happen through methods but then there's these hidden methods okay let's
take a look at the code so i'll create a dictionary named x and then we say x sub 1 equals 40 and again
we know what this means that means somewhere in the key the key under the key one there's 40
now i can print this out by saying x dot double underscore get item double underscore open paren
one close print that's taking the index inside of the square brackets and passing it to a predefined
python understood rule for what get item that the square brackets turn into double underscore get
item double underscore where the x is the object and the parameter is the syntax so if we think
about it on the right hand side of an assignment statement where we're just reading it it's just
doing the get right it's kind of doing a getter like thing give me item one and then out comes
the 40 and that's how the print of x sub 1 is a 40 that's really what happens under the covers is
there is a class which has underscore underscore get item underscore underscore defined in it as
a method and that's how it loads x sub 1 so if we go down another line and we say x sub 5 equals
x sub 1 plus 2 seems simple enough and and literally for years python software developers
don't even need to know that this is miraculously and beautifully complex but what this translates
into at runtime by compiler syntax transformation is the x sub 1 on the right hand side turns into
a x dot get item paren one which pulls up the 40 and then plus 2 gets added to it but then that
expression is passed into x dot set item in position five so the the left hand side of
the assignment statement is the x sub 5 equals part and that's calling set item so if it's doing
a square bracket look up on the right hand side it's calling get item and if it's doing a square
bracket on the left hand side of an assignment statement it's doing a set item so this means
that there was no need to return references no need to process references none of the hoops
that c++ went through and so you see that python did not did not choose to implement
the way c++ did but they supported the very elegant syntax now and then you'll see that java
in 1995 takes it or 94 takes it one step further in that they're not even going to give you that
cool syntax they're like no we're going to say just do x dot put and x dot get and call it good
if you if you know that x is an object and you need to do a get in the put do the get in the put
we're not going to do this little syntax transformation that makes it pretty and we're
also not going to give you uh operator overloading because again operator overloading requires
references because it allows the class to return a thing that can be used on either the left or
right hand side and again java did that because they did not want to make their memory management
more complex so it's hard to argue but what this kind of shows you is like the amazing
interplay between these languages yarn stro strip went to school in denmark and started working on
c++ in denmark but then was hired to go to bell labs in new jersey where he met and worked with
for a number of years uh yarn stro strip and dennis richie and all the folks at bell labs
that gave us unix and c over the decades and so c++ kind of came to the world from bell labs from
murray hill and and guido van rossum who was in netherlands at the time really was just looking
at all this stuff and using all this stuff and an expert in c and c++ and back in those days we
tended to look a lot at like the code that c++ generated and guido's like i'm just gonna i'm
gonna borrow these are really good patterns and so that's how we see so much influence of not just
the syntax but the actual runtime conventions and and like if you if you look at some of the generated
c++ code the concept of private is often done with underscores they use underscores a lot
python's like yeah i'll just borrow that i'll just use double underscore as my
signal is as private and away you go so to show the influence that c++ and c had over python both
in the syntax and in the runtime you can take a quick look at some internal details of how python
works and python turns out to almost identically implemented operator overloading in as as c++ but
we don't see it it's all internal you have to kind of look so on on the left hand side that's
the code that i just got done going through that's the c++ code that has the private values and then
the public operator overload and now if we look on the right hand side we see a class tenant and
i'm creating a double underscore values which is values private as a dictionary and then i'm going
to define the set item so this is like a private method called set item and then private method
called get item python basically has the left side and right side assignment of a bracket lookup
operators different and the set item is the left hand side and the get item is the right hand side
you'll see that in the set item i'm just taking self values sub index equals value and i'm in the
in the getter i'm returning self underscore values sub index so that's the right hand side so if we
look at the code i see let's make a tenant on the variable 10 10 sub 1 equals 40 now python transforms
that 10 sub 1 syntax into a set item of 10 comma the number 1 comma 40 and then call set item and
you can see of course it worked right it the three values are self index and value well self is 10
which is the object instance the index is the thing inside the square brackets and the value
is the result of the expression on the right hand side it's not just 40 but it's the expression on
the right hand side and so that goes in right we see the print 10 sub 1 well that is a right hand
side reference to 10 sub 1 so that's going to call get item self is 10 and then index is the 1 and
we're going to just return it and that's going to print out a nice little happy little integer
which is exactly the variable 40 so it says 10 sub 1 contains 40 and at this point it should be
obvious what's going on when i say 10 sub 5 equals 10 sub 1 plus 2 well the 10 sub 1 on the right hand
side turns into a get item that gives us back the 40 value then the 40 and the two are added
together to finish the right hand side of the expression then we're going to sign that into 10
sub 5 which then turns into a set item of 10 comma 5 comma 42 and then that stores 42 in position 5
in our private variable values private values variable and then i printed out which is left hand
side lookup of 10 sub 5 which calls get item again with self is 10 and index is 5 and so we get the
42 and so you see how they're so similar inside i mean again like if you look at generated c++
code from early c++ code compilers you'll see these double underscores used in various places
which means that python in its internal implementation use the same patterns as c++ did
in its internal implementation python chose not to do call by reference and return by reference
java chose not to be not to do call by reference and return by reference and java chose not to do
the fancy syntax transformation but you know who knows maybe maybe one of these days java could do
that syntax transformation and be like whoa java has everything and then to some degree python has
shown the way about how you do this without doing um without doing call call by reference and again
that ampersand operator and ampersand index on the left hand side that's the like scary part where
language designers are like oh sure i want to go do that because c++ is not a garbage collected
language but python and java are garbage collected languages and that's not the only reason
that's that python and java didn't want to do call by reference but it is one of the reasons that you
kind of just simplifies to know that there when a function is done it's done and there's not like
sneaky little pointers inside that function that need to stay alive so it allows you to throw stuff
away when functions are finished okay enough of that just again i'm just trying to show you in the
simplest possible examples the kinds of design decisions that all these languages and library
designers were doing as they built the languages that we know love and use today