- Welcome to C Programming for Everybody.
My name's Charles Severance,
and I'm your instructor for this course.
This course and website is dedicated to learning
the classic version of C programming language
from the 1978 book written by Brian W. Kernigan
and Dennis M. Ritchie.
This book places the reader in the middle
of the 1970s transition from a hardware-centered
computer science to a focus on writing portable
and efficient software.
C was used to develop operating systems
like Unix, Minix, and Linux.
Programming languages like Perl, Python, Java,
and JavaScript and Ruby are all written in C.
Software like early TCP/IP networking stack implementations
that made the internet possible were written in C.
And the first web browsers and web servers
were written in C.
Writing software in C enabled major advances
in computer architecture and performance.
Operating systems, compilers, and utilities
could be recompiled to work on a new hardware platform
once we had a C compiler for the new hardware.
So much software has been written in C
over the past 40 years that there's a very good chance
that much of the software that you use every day
was either written in C or written in a programming language
that was written in C.
So we study C less as a programming language
to use on a daily basis and more as the foundation
of modern software and computing.
In many ways, C is the technology equivalent
of the Rosetta Stone in that it provides a connection
between the programming languages of the past
and the programming languages of the present.
The name CC4E in www.cc4e.com
refers to the original Unix command CC,
which was the command that you used
to compile your C program.
CC stood for C compiler and it is featured on the first page
of the first chapter of the KNRC book.
Programmers like me from the 1970s and 1980s
type CC on Unix systems like the AT&T 3B2
to compile and run their first Hello World program in C.
This material is being presented under fair use
as we are making use of material from a copyrighted work
that is out of print and not broadly available
in any format.
The book is also not available in any accessible format.
We are making use of this material
in a teaching and research context
with a focus on studying its contribution
to computing history.
The material is available for free and online
to anyone who wants to learn about the history
of the C language, computing, and computer architecture.
Welcome to the course.