- Hello, and welcome to C Programming for Everybody.
This lecture is putting C in a bit of a historical context.
Now, if you're watching this lecture,
you're probably familiar with some of my other classes.
I just wanna kinda let you know
that I've been building a lot of classes.
Most of you probably took Python for Everybody,
available on Coursera, edX, and many other platforms.
But I have a whole series of classes that are designed,
what I call the path of the master programmer,
where I try to start people that,
no matter where you start,
I want you to be able to learn to be a really good programmer
and you follow along as far as you want.
These are all my materials.
They're all 100% free, open, and online.
And they're really aimed at teaching everybody
how to program.
I mean, I started doing this back in 2012 with Coursera.
And I have dedicated myself to making all my materials free
and to create a path that anyone can take anywhere
in the world, regardless of economic challenges
or other things in your life.
I want everybody to have an opportunity
to be a professional developer.
So I encourage you.
And frankly, if you haven't taken Python yet,
like my Python for Everybody class,
this course is going to be a little bit difficult.
So let's start with a history of C.
The book we're looking at, The Kernigan and Ritchie,
a C programming language by Brian W. Kernigan
and Dennis M. Ritchie, was published in 1978.
And the key thing is that it is a moment in history
where everything changed.
And so we're looking at this textbook
and the text in this textbook and the language itself
in the context of how it has impacted history.
The C programming language itself has a long history.
There was a language called B,
and they were using it at AT&T Abel Labs
to build utilities and operating system stuff.
But it was a little too word-oriented.
And so the language C was,
as new computer hardware came out,
that supported byte addressing
and the ability to load a string of bytes
and store a string of bytes rather than a set of words,
words being larger than a byte
and more than one character were packed into words,
and kind of like the '60s and early '70s.
C wanted to make a character,
a sort of core low-level VAP kind of data
that the language would happen.
And from like the early and mid '70s,
the C and Unix kind of co-evolved.
They wanted to build something
that would make Unix work well on a PDP 1120,
and at the same time,
make it so they could port Unix to other systems.
But really, it was about the PDP 1120's
cool memory architecture
having to do with byte addressability.
And what happened was is they were
carefully rewriting Unix in C,
but then fixing C, laying the groundwork
for Unix portability.
And so by 1978, this KNRC book was published.
And at that point, you could think of it as a summary
of over a decade of research in how to build
a portable programming language,
and then use that portable programming language
to build a portable operating system,
C and Unix, of course.
By 1989, C had become popular,
and there was a need to standardize it.
So there's a variant of C called C89.
That is the ANSI.
And then that same version was called C90,
is ISO, the International Organization of Standards,
also standardized that.
And so that was our first version of the C
that we could all agree on.
The ANSI did not intend to go too far away
from what we call KNRC,
but instead it just sort of nailed down a few things
that by then were important to nail down.
And C has continued to evolve
from sort of 1990 to the present,
and there's a number of major revisions.
But the key thing that these revisions don't do
in the modern version of C
is they do not attempt to make C
easy to use language, say like Python or JavaScript.
And then C knows its place in the panoply of languages
and does a good job of that.
So if we look at sort of what's the future,
C is a difficult language to use
as a general purpose language.
Python is a great general purpose language,
but it's not a great systems programming language.
And the two things that are missing from C
are the lack of really solid dynamic memory support
in the core types and libraries.
And then there is no safe string type.
Strings are not, there's no string in C,
it's character arrays, and arrays have sizes.
And if you start putting stuff
beyond the boundary of that array, things just blow up.
And C++ is, to me, not the sort of future version of C.
It's really a more powerful, intricate,
and flexible version of C for programmers
who are doing really professional,
intricate systems applications.
Writing good C++ in some ways
is more difficult than writing good C.
The languages that sort of take on C's mantle
in the general purpose are things like Java,
JavaScript, C#, or Python.
The key thing with these languages
is they don't give you sort of strings
as just raw byte arrays.
And they give us a simple object-oriented layer
that keeps us away from the metal.
The goal of C is to get close to the hardware,
close to the metal.
And so Java, JavaScript, C#, Python
are all great languages,
and they're great for what we use them for.
They're just not well suited
for writing an operating system kernel.
The most likely language that is like C,
like the next C, is probably Rust.
The idea of Rust is that it stays close to the metal,
but then gives us some simple and safe core data types.
And recently, Linux is starting to accept some Rust in Linux.
And so that means that Rust has to be mature.
It means that Rust can't be evolving rapidly.
I've seen situations where operating systems
like macOS decide to depend on Python.
So there's parts of macOS that depend on Python 2,
but then they can't really upgrade to Python 2
because of their operating system, blah, blah, blah.
So for an operating system to depend
on a programming language like Rust,
it really has to be mature and,
even more importantly, stable.
You can't have clever innovations
in the programming language causing regressions
in an operating system, say like Linux.
So look for Rust.
Now, C has been around a long time.
Before C, we'll call C starting in '72,
the book is published in '78.
Before C, most of us would write a semilanguage or Fortran.
Some people wrote PL/1 that's not on here.
Fortran is not really a general purpose programming language.
You wouldn't write a command like cat in Fortran.
Fortran was really for scientific computations.
And the earliest of computers in the '50s, '60s
were either sort of really specialized
toward like payroll and HR systems,
or they were really specialized to doing computations.
And the ones that specialized were the science ones
were used Fortran 'cause it was just the right language
for those computers that were aimed
at doing scientific calculations.
C as a language was kind of none of the above
in that it was aimed at writing system code, a kernel,
an operating system, and the utilities around it,
including like other languages.
And so C is kind of the mother tongue
of all kinds of other derivative languages.
And things like the Bash shell, Perl, Python, PHP,
C++, JavaScript, Java, and C# and Objective-C
just kind of were derivatives of this beginning of C.
And that's why you see a lot of patterns
in these other languages that are similar.
And that's because JavaScript and Java
both inherited their for loop syntax from C.
So I've got a couple of videos in this section.
This is Brian Kernigan talking about
the C programming language and it's a short video.
I didn't produce this video, but it's a great little video.
Another video is from the creator of C++, Bjorn Stroestrup.
This was an interview that I did
with IEEE Computer Magazine.
On top of this history of the C language,
we can look at a brief history of computers.
And I have a whole course
called Internet History, Technology, and Security
that really starts in the 1940s
with a focus more on communication rather than computation,
even though communication and computation
were very much connected throughout the 40s
through even today.
In the early 1950s, computers were,
you best think of them as like
a multimillion dollar strategic asset.
Every single computer.
And a lot of them were custom built.
The first computer at Michigan State University
where I went to undergrad was built
by the electrical engineering students of that university
based on some designs that they borrowed, I think,
from Iowa.
And so things like the programming language,
the operating system,
you didn't have a lot of generalization.
You didn't have a lot of sharing.
You tended to write code and put it on a paper tape,
or later a magnetic tape, and load it and run it.
And so you were just pretty happy if the code worked.
You didn't need an operating system.
These weren't multiprocessing computers.
And so the software environment was very minimalist.
But in the late '50s and early '60s,
you saw companies like IBM
and Digital Equipment Corporation
began selling general purpose computers.
They just couldn't make them.
And they started selling them.
And they still were expensive,
and they were only in like,
a business would have a couple of computers
to help them do payroll, perhaps, or something like that.
Something that was really, really important
'cause the computers were expensive.
But in the '60s,
there, we really got to the point
where the computer componentry, the chips, et cetera,
were becoming commodities.
You could just go to a place and buy chips.
And then you could make a computer
by buying a bunch of chips
and putting those things together.
And because you weren't building everything from scratch,
the cost got a lot lower.
The other thing that these less expensive computers were
is they were a little slower.
But by the end of the 1960s, there was a lot of computers.
There were some super expensive, weird, one-off,
small production computers.
There were computers that had,
there was like the previous generation of mini-computer
where there were lots of them
laying around old computer science departments
or businesses that they weren't sure
what they did to do with them.
They wanted to buy a new one.
And then there were just innovative,
new, low-cost computers coming out.
And in the '70s, in this milieu of just lots
of new and old computer hardware,
the question was is there a way we can do things
with all of this old hardware?
And is there sort of one solution?
And that's where Unix NC came.
And certainly after the '70s, we look at the '80s,
and that's where microprocessors and personal computers.
And so we went from computers
that were sizes of refrigerators or desks
to the size of a computer could be on a single chip.
And in the beginning, those personal computers
like the IBM PC or Commodore PET,
they had really bad performance, but that performance,
once you could get everything on a single chip,
that performance could get faster very quickly.
And because personal computers became a mass market item,
a lot of money could be invested in personal computers.
By the 1990s, personal computers continued to grow, right?
And, but the need to communicate and talk
and exchange information became important.
And so in the 1990s, we saw really an increasing focus
on connecting computers with the internet
and other kinds of networks.
And the performance of these computers
and the price kept going down, the performance kept going up.
And then by the time we get to the 2000s,
Amazon's AWS was founded in 2002,
and it used personal computer microprocessors
like from Intel and produced computing as a commodity, right?
And so, and you don't even buy computers anymore.
You just go to Amazon and say,
I'll rent a computer for $7 a month.
And so we see in 1978, we see this moment
where the computers were becoming more common,
they're going down in price,
and there's getting to be more and more of them.
And there was a diversity of computers.
These days, there's actually less diversity.
If we go back in history,
and you take a look at my internet history class,
you can see the, I go to Bletchley Park
and show you some of the earliest computations
from the 1940s and World War II.
We go to Computer History Museum in California
and visit with Gordon Bell and talk about the PDP-1.
And he talks a lot about buying the components
and putting the components together
and how sort of the mass availability
of relatively low-cost components really allowed
for a rapid innovation in computer architecture.
A computer that I used in my computer science degree
was the Control Data CDC 6500.
And I have a video where we visit
the Living Computer Museum in Seattle, Washington,
and hear card readers work and card punches.
And if we ever get to the point
where everything opens back up again,
it's a tremendous visit to go see all the technology
that really through the years,
except that in the Living Computer Museum,
they like to have everything running.
And then you can take a look at a more modern,
smaller Raspberry Pi,
which the Raspberry Pi is actually not an Intel-based system.
The Raspberry Pi is based on ARM,
the processor that really became popular
as a result of the cell phone revolution.
And so the Raspberry Pi is to take
what the technology was advanced,
both low-power and high-performance technology
that was advanced because of mobile phone innovations.
The Raspberry Pi came out
and was a good single-board computer.
So let's take a look at the operating system.
Unix is the operating system that is connected with C.
In the 1960s, there was a multi-user operating system
called Multics.
And then in the 1970s,
they wanted to come up with yet another operating system,
and they eventually called it Unix,
and the DEC PDP1120,
which was one of these new commodity part-based computers
that was coming into the marketplace.
And so in 1973, Unix was rewritten in C,
but it only was there on the PDP11,
although they had laid the groundwork for portability
from the beginning.
They knew they wanted to have everything be portable.
They just couldn't make it all portable.
The first version,
they just had to make it run on the PDP11.
And then by 1978, the Unix,
the second computer that Unix had run on
was an Interdata 832,
and that was quite a different computer.
And so it was good.
And so they really learned a lot about making Unix
a portable bit of software.
In the early 1970s, C was evolving in a way
so that the Unix could be ported, right?
So it's like, let's,
we got this problem between, let's just say,
the PDP11 and the Interdata.
And how can we fix this?
And we can both change how the operating system works.
We can change the operating system code,
and we can change the C compiler,
and then we can rewrite the operating system code
to get less and less assembly language
and more and more C language.
And so the idea was to get to the point
where there was a very, very small amount
of assembly language in Unix.
And over the years, that's gotten lower and lower.
Unix was rewritten.
A number of versions came out in the '70s,
having to do with their portability.
So by 1978, the Unix version 7 could also run
on a whole new architecture from DEC called the VAX systems.
University of California, Berkeley
had their own distribution of Unix called BSD,
the Berkeley Software Distribution.
And that was really cool
because universities often pushed things like networking,
TCP/IP, ARPANET.
BSD Unix was the first place some of us saw TCP/IP.
1982, a company based solely on Unix
called Sun Microsystems was found.
Sun was some work at Stanford, some work at Berkeley,
all based on Unix, and they created
what in effect was the Unix Workstation Marketplace.
At this point, you could imagine that the world was about
to just adopt Unix.
Unix was the greatest thing ever.
Computer science departments were teaching Unix
in their operating systems classes in the mid '80s.
The problem became AT&T had never come up really
with a business plan for what the purpose of Unix was,
and so there was some fits and starts
as to how they could monetize this extremely popular thing.
And they didn't do a great job,
and it took them a long time to figure out
what was going to be successful.
And by the time AT&T sort of figured things out,
the market had moved on.
And so Minix is an operating system
that was developed in the Netherlands by Andrew Tannenbaum,
and he built a completely free
and open source operating system
that was used for education.
He built a textbook around it, and it was very popular.
But he didn't want commercialization,
at least not at that point in time,
so he sort of held onto it too tightly.
Again, kind of an intellectual property mistake.
And in 1991, a program called Linus Torvalds decided
he was going to build a fresh ground-up implementation
of the Unix kernel that was 100% free.
So he wasn't going to use Unix.
He wasn't going to use Minix.
He wanted to create another thing.
And originally, it was just like a hobby.
I'm going to try to see how far I can go.
By 1992, Linux started to work,
and it adopted this license called the GPL,
which is called the GNU Public Library License,
which is a strongly open source license
in the way that it's difficult
to take Linux out of open source,
which meant that people could then invest in Linux.
And so Linux has become Unix, right?
Linux in the modern world is the Unix-like system.
And Unix tried to hold on for a while,
but they really, really couldn't.
And so the remaining Unix distributions
are a tiny, tiny fraction of the marketplace,
and Linux is the marketplace.
So we can see some of this in some of the videos
that I've got, like Andrew Tannenbaum
will tell us the story of how Minix was created
and how Minix kind of begat Linux,
and so that there's some interesting stuff here, okay?
So I'll lay on top of all this.
Remember that 1978 is this moment in history
where I claim like everything changed.
Now I've been a computer scientist for a very long time.
I started in 1975.
And in 1975, I learned things like Fortran on a computer,
that CDC 6500 computer.
It ran a special operating system called Scope Hustler.
I knew how to do assembly, I knew Fortran,
and even Pascal.
So Pascal in the '70s was one of these languages that,
and I've got a video for Pascal as well,
one of these languages that was sort of like saying,
"Look, here's the future."
Now Pascal was really aimed at teaching,
and so I used Pascal in educational context.
And as I became a professional programmer in the 1980s,
I was using a bunch of stuff.
Assembly language, COBOL, a little bit of Unix and C here.
It wasn't like by the early '80s, Unix was everywhere,
at least not in the professional world,
because the PC revolution was happening.
So we had DOS, we had early Windows versions.
I used things like DBase and Turbo Pascal.
I taught classes of the IBM 360,
and I taught assembly language.
I used the DECVAX, and I used the VMS, not Unix operating
system and Fortran.
And I also then taught in the mid '80s on an AT&T Western,
I think it's called, a GE AT&T 3B2.
I taught Unix, I taught C, and I taught Fortran.
And so even though we can trace back to like 1978
is the moment that everything changed,
it's not like the market changed.
The thing that happened in the 1990s though,
is that all these older computers and the older computers,
vendors like Burrows and Unisys and IBM and Cray
and Control Data, as microprocessor speeds increased,
all these little companies would create Unix workstations
that were faster and faster and faster.
And because they could build new hardware that was fast
and then grab the Unix operating system
and make their operating system work on their new hardware,
it allowed for some amazing innovation.
So I was using Sun, Ardent, Stellar, these are all gone now.
IBM RS6000, Convex C2400, I had a Next on my desk,
I use C, but TCP/IP, Windows, HTTP, the web, you know,
and Windows and Mac OS were all kind of in the mix.
But the innovation was really happening most rapidly
in the Unix space.
But by the 2000s, everything that I touched
really had some aspect, I'm not a Windows person,
so everything I touched had some aspect of Unix in it.
Mac OS still has Unix in it, Linux and my languages
are sort of narrowing back down to Java, PHP and JavaScript.
And then in 2010s, right?
Linux, Mac OS, Python, PHP, JavaScript.
So things really have settled into a world
that my own software development,
where I'm pretty much using Unix-like systems all the time
and C-based or C-derived languages,
'cause Python, Java, PHP and JavaScript are all based on C.
And that's why it's so important to understand C.
I'm not writing C as a professional in any way,
but I am using all my C knowledge every single day.
And so that's sort of a picture of me in my office,
that's an IBM PS/2 in my office.
I was registering in 1989,
I was registering with punch cards.
When I first started, I was using a line printer
and punch cards and so there's my history.
Now, I think it's important to acknowledge
that as I've shown you all these history documents
and the videos and the oral histories that I've done,
is there is a preponderance of old white males in here.
And I think that it is important to talk a bit about that
and why that is perhaps.
And so I would encourage you to take a look at an article,
so NPR article, it's actually, you can listen to it,
about what happened to computer science.
The title of the article is "When Women Stop Coding."
All the way up to 1980,
computer science was just another field.
And then it kept going up to sort of 1985,
but then it went down and so all these other fields
have a pretty good gender mix
and the computer science does not have a gender mix.
And so I would encourage you to listen to this article.
Another area that you can learn something about,
the diversity in computer science is this book
by Jane Margolis called "Unlocking the Clubhouse."
The essence of the book is really talking
about how social pressure, advertising pressure
in the early '80s made it seem
as though computing was a guy thing.
And in particular, it made it so that young men,
even in high school,
would go fiddle around with computers as a hobby.
And by the time they got to college, they were pretty skilled.
And if you weren't skilled, the college classes were designed
for people who already knew what programming was.
And if you were a woman and you hadn't played with computers
in 1980, when you were like 14 years old,
you came to college at a distinct disadvantage.
And this is what led to this fall off
where colleges tended to teach to programmers
who already knew how to program.
And that really meant that the hobbyists,
people who were in their youth before they went to college
and played with programming as a hobby
had a tremendous advantage.
Now, Jane did her work in the '80s, late '80s and '90s.
I myself am older than that.
And I think that to some degree,
this notion of the social pressure
that said that computing was really for young men
and not young woman, it's actually as much a symptom
as it is the cause.
Because I grew up in a time in the mid '70s
where there were women everywhere.
And this is a person who had a really large impact
in my life, her name is Helen Spence.
She was a professor at Michigan State University
and I show you a URL to look at her oral history.
She taught me operating systems.
So in 1977 or 1978, I don't remember when,
Helen was my operating systems teacher.
The interesting thing about how Helen taught
operating systems was she made it fun.
It was really fun.
I encountered my first auto grader in Helen's class.
She had made a piece of software
that she called the HMS 5050,
which itself is both Helen Spence
and I think it's Her Majesty's ship at the same time.
And what she did was she built a operating system simulator
in Fortran and our job as taking the class
was to build functions and subroutines
that would implement the tasks and the algorithms
that operating systems need to do.
So you'd run your program over and over and over again
until you had written a successful operating system
and she wrote a auto grader that would do things
to your program and then measure whether or not
you knew how to build an operating system.
It was just a natural thing to have females
as faculty members and there was a lot more fun
in the field and I have my own theories
that I think compliment Jane's theories as well
but I'll leave it here that that's a TED talk
for another day as to gender and computing.
Right now I'm just acknowledging it
and giving you some resources to read
and reach your own conclusions.
If you look at everything I've done since 2012
in the free online education in MOOC space,
you'll notice that every course I've ever created
has the words for everybody
and that's not just a marketing thing,
that's because it's my philosophy.
If you've taken some of my classes like Python
for everybody or Django for everybody,
web applications for everybody, Postgres for everybody
and now C programming for everybody,
I try to build a course where I spend time
thinking about how not to create the clubhouse
that Jane talks about and that is I want you in the club,
I want everybody in the club,
I don't want it just to be a club for the super geniuses
and so part of why I'm building an entire curriculum
is to perhaps just make a new club
and that is programming for everybody club
and I think once you become a great programmer,
I think that's a good time to study computer science
and so perhaps after we teach everybody programming,
then we can teach everybody computer science
but again, that's a TED talk for another day.
So on to the course, C programming for everybody.
I'll just say that C is the most important
programming language you're going to ever learn.
It should never be the first programming language
taught to any students.
You will likely never write a line of C
in a professional context in your career.
I'm not teaching you C so that you can go
be a professional C programmer.
I'm teaching you C so you can be
a professional Java programmer really
but if you learn C at the right time
in your learning journey,
it's a necessary step on the path
to becoming a master programmer
but it's an important step
'cause I can't teach you Java
if I hadn't already taught you C.
I have to explain how Java works
in terms of what you're going to learn in this class.
So this class is not just like get a C certificate
and go make lots of money
'cause I don't think that this certificate's
going to make you a lot of money
but I do think this certificate is going to unlock
the future of you as a programmer.
So please be patient with this material.
Do not rush.
It's an online class.
I guarantee that you can search for solutions
to every programming exercise that I create.
I don't change them that much
so the solutions are out there
and if your goal is to game it
and just search for solutions to programming,
go ahead, finish the class.
Congratulations.
But you have just taken the opportunity
to learn from yourself, right?
You didn't trick me.
I didn't lose anything by you searching for
and just pasting in solutions to programs.
Each exercise from beginning to end
is trying to take you a little tiny step further
down your understanding.
And the easy exercises in the beginning,
even if I have a bunch of them,
they're there to prepare and strengthen you
for something much more challenging in the course.
If you start pasting in solutions
in the beginning of the course,
you have no chance in the end of the course
and you're just gonna be pasting in solutions
and when you do that, you'll have only wasted your time.
So, I look forward to you taking the rest of this course.
Of course, I look forward to you telling me
if I'm right in my instinct
about how important this is for you,
especially after you take a few more classes
and then find your way to being a professional.
(gentle music)